Emile van Krieken

Research Associate - University of Edinburgh

info@emilevankrieken.com emilevankrieken.com

I am a Research Associate (Postdoc) at the University of Edinburgh, working on Artificial Intelligence. My main research interest is Neurosymbolic methods for machine learning. I obtained my PhD in 2024 at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam.

Education

PhD – Cum Laude (top 5%)

Amsterdam, NL

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

Apr 2019 - Jan 2024

Dissertation title: "Optimisation in Neurosymbolic Learning Systems"

Supervised by prof. Annette ten Teije and dr. Jakub Tomczak.

Doctorate committee: prof. Mark Hoogendoorn, prof. Luc de Raedt, prof. Cassio de Campos, dr. Sebastijan Dumancic, dr. Efi Tsamoura

Master in Artificial Intelligence – Cum Laude

Amsterdam, NL

University of Amsterdam

Sep 2016-Feb 2019

Average 9.0/10.0 (4.00 GPA)

- Thesis: "Differentiable Fuzzy Logics". Grade: 9.5/10.0. Supervisors: prof. Frank van Harmelen, dr. Erman Acar. Assessor: dr. Thomas Kipf.

Bachelor in Computer Science – Cum Laude

Utrecht, NL

Universiteit Utrecht

Sep 2013-Jun 2016

Average 8.7/10.0 (4.00 GPA)

Work Experience

Research Associate (Postdoc)

Edinburgh, United Kingdom

University of Edinburgh

Since Sep 2023

Working in the "Edinburgh Laboratory for Integrated Artificial Intelligence" (ELIAI) under the supervision of dr. Pasquale Minervini, dr. Antonio Vergari and dr. Edoardo Ponti. The project is on gradient-based learning of discrete structures.

Research Visit Trento, Italy

Fondazione Bruno Kessler

Sep 2021-Oct 2021

Project together with dr. Alessandro Daniele and prof. Luciano Serafini on Neurosymbolic AI. Funded by the HumaneAI EU Horizon project.

Research Assistant Amsterdam, NL

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

Sep 2017-Feb 2018

Supervised by dr. Jacqueline Heinerman, on social learning in robotics.

Treasurer Utrecht, NL

DWARS, GroenLinkse Jongeren

Oct 2016-Jul 2017

Composer and Programmer

Breda, NL

Gilded Games

Jun 2011-Nov 2015

- Worked with an international team on large and successful modifications for Minecraft, such as 'The Aether'.

Publications

- Gema, A. P., Leang, J. O. J., Hong, G., Devoto, A., Mancino, A. C. M., Saxena, R., ... van Krieken, E., Minervini, P. Are We Done with MMLU? Preprint 2024
- Bortolotti, S., Marconato, E., Carraro, T., Morettin, P., van Krieken, E., Vergari, A., ... Passerini, A. A Benchmark Suite for Systematically Evaluating Reasoning Shortcuts. Preprint 2024
- van Krieken, E.*, Badreddine, S.*, Manhaeve, R., Giunchiglia, E. ULLER: A Unified Language for Learning and Reasoning. 18th International Conference on Neural-Symbolic Learning and Reasoning (NeSy 2024)
- van Krieken, E., Minervini, P., Ponti, E., Vergari, A. On the Independence Assumption in Neurosymbolic Learning. In Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2024)
- Marconato, E.*, Bortolotti, S.*, van Krieken, E.*, Vergari, A., Passerini, A., Teso, S. BEARS
 Make Neuro-Symbolic Models Aware of their Reasoning Shortcuts. 40th Conference on Uncertainty
 in Artificial Intelligence (UAI 2024)
- T. Younesian, T. Thanapalasingam, E. van Krieken, D. Daza, P. Bloem. "GRAPES: Learning to Sample Graphs for Scalable Graph Neural Networks." Preprint 2024
- T. Thanapalasingam, E. van Krieken, P. Bloem, P. Groth. "Intelligraphs: Datasets for Benchmarking Knowledge Graph Generation." Preprint 2023
- E. van Krieken, T. Thanapalasingam, J. Tomczak, A. Ten Teije, F. van Harmelen. "A-NeSI: Scalable Approximate Inference for Probabilistic Neurosymbolic Learning." Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 36 (NeurIPS 2023)
- Alessandro Daniele*, **E. van Krieken***, L. Serafini, F. van Harmelen. "Refining neural network predictions using background knowledge." Machine Learning 112 (9), 3293-3331
- E. van Krieken, E. Acar, F. van Harmelen. "Analyzing differentiable fuzzy logic operators." Artificial Intelligence 302 2022
- K. van den Houten, E. van Krieken, B. Heidergott. "Analysis of Measure-Valued Derivatives in a Reinforcement Learning Actor-Critic Framework." Winter Simulation Conference 2022
- D. Alivanistos, S. B. Santamaria, M. Cochez, J.C. Kalo, **E. van Krieken**, T. Thanapalasingam. "Prompting as probing: Using language models for knowledge base construction." LM-KBC challenge at ISWC 2022, Track 2 winner
- E. van Krieken, J. Tomczak, A. Ten Teije. "Storchastic: A framework for general stochastic automatic differentiation." Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 34 (NeurIPS 2021)
- K. Grouwstra, **E. van Krieken**. "Type-driven Neural Programming by Example." NeurIPS 2020 Workshop on Computer-Assisted Programming
- E. van Krieken, E. Acar, F. van Harmelen. "Analyzing differentiable fuzzy implications." Proceedings of the International Conference on Principles of Knowledge Representation and Reasoning. Vol. 17. No. 1. 2020 (KR 2020)
- E. van Krieken, E. Acar, F. van Harmelen. "Semi-Supervised Learning using Differentiable Reasoning." Journal of Applied Logic 6.4 2019

• J. Heinerman, B. Bussmann, R. Groenendijk, **E. Van Krieken**, J. Slik, A. Tezza, A. E. Eiben. "Benefits of social learning in physical robots". IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence (SSCI) 2018

Additional education

International Artificial Intelligence in Bergen Research School

Bergen, Norway

University of Bergen

Jun~2022

Topic: Knowledge Graphs and Machine Learning.

Explore Entrepreneurship

Amsterdam, NL

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

May 2021

Topic: An introduction to entrepreneurship and startups.

Research methods and methodology for IKS

Vught, NL

 $School\ for\ Information\ and\ Knowledge\ Systems$

Nov 2019

Topic: Setting up large research projects.

Cambridge Professional English

Breda, NL

Stedelijk Gymnasium Breda

Sep~2006-Jun~2012

Teaching

• Deep Learning, 2020, 2021, 2022 (Master AI Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam). Teaching assistant, gave two lectures on Reinforcement Learning.

- Student supervision
 - Jochem Herrebrugh (2022, BSc VU)
 - Kim van den Houten (2021, MSc VU). Won 2021 Extrie Thesis Award.
 - Kiara Grouwstra (2020, MSc UvA)

Talks

- SIKS Course on Neural-Symbolic AI (June 2024, invited)
- Machine Learning for Graphs course, Amsterdam (Jan 2024, invited)
- NeurIPS 2023 (Dec 2023, A-NeSI poster)
- New Frontiers in Graph Learning workshop at NeurIPS 2023 (Dec 2023, GRAPES poster)
- GFlowNet reading club at MILa Quebec AI Institute (Nov 2023, invited)
- SMiLe workshop 2023 (June 2023, invited talk and poster)
- NeSy-GeMs workshop at ICLR 2023 (May 2023, poster)
- GFlowNet reading club at MILA Quebec AI Institute (April 2023, invited)
- ILCC/CDT NLP Seminar series at University of Edinburgh (March 2023, invited)
- Algorithms group at TU Delft (Feb 2023, invited)
- AMLAB group at University of Amsterdam (Oct 2022, invited)
- DTAI group at KU Leuven (Sep 2022, invited)

^{*} denotes equal contribution

- IJCLR (Sep 2022, oral)
- Logic and Learning Seminar, Bergen (Aug 2022, invited)
- RL Summer School 2022 in Amsterdam (Jul 2022, invited, lecture on policy gradients)
- HHAI 2022 KR4HI Workshop (Jun 2022, extended abstract)
- International Artificial Intelligence in Bergen Research School (Jun 2022, invited, **best** presentation award)
- BeNeRL 2022 (Jun 2022, Storchastic poster)
- NeurIPS 2021 (Dec 2021, Storchastic poster)
- DKM Unit seminar, Fondazione Bruno Kessler (Sep 2021, invited)
- Pyro Seminar, Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard (Jun 2021, invited, about Storchastic)
- DWS colloquium, Universität Mannheim (Nov 2020, invited)
- KR2020 (Oct 2020, oral)

Miscellaneous

- Co-lead of organising committee for Neurosymbolic Generative Models (NeSy-GeMs) workshop at ICLR 2023. Tasks: Proposal writing, website, social media and email maintenance, program chair, setting up the program committee, and moderation during the workshop day.
- Organised a symposium on Probabilistic Learning and Reasoning at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam in 2024 before my PhD defence.
- \bullet We won the LM-KBC challenge at ISWC 2022.
- National research evaluation informatics (2015-2020) of the department of computer science, VU Amsterdam (2022). Role: Represent PhD students.
- Acted as an evaluator of ELLIS PhD applications (2023).
- Consulting for Flagship Pioneering (2023). Created an Obsidian plugin.
- Reviewing:
 - Conferences: ICML 2024, NeSy 2024, NeurIPS 2023, KR 2023, AISTATS 2022, 2023, 2024,
 CIKM 2020, AAAI 2020
 - Journals: TMLR, JMLR, JBHI, JAIR, Operations Research
- Open Source Software
 - Storchastic: A PyTorch library for general gradient estimation.
 - Juggl: A plugin for the Obsidian note-taking app which adds an advanced and customizable graph view.
 - Made significant contributions to other popular Obsidian plugins: Supercharged Links, Breadcrumbs, Graph Analysis and Search on Internet.